Ana Carolina Silveira Calado Siqueira Barbosa

lacktriangledaphia PA lacktriangledaphia anacarolina.calado@gmail.com lacktriangledaphia +1 (470) 302 2021 lacketerangledaphia anacarolina.calado.github.io

in Ana Carolina S Calado S Barbosa, MS

Bio

I am a nutritionist with a Master's degree in Human Nutrition and a certification in Maternal and Child Nutrition, focusing on both clinical and molecular aspects. I have extensive experience in managing chronic diseases, including kidney disease, obesity, and diabetes, with a particular focus on vulnerable populations for 14 years. In recent years, my work has increasingly engaged with public policy and social justice issues in Latin America and the United States, particularly food insecurity and its relationship to chronic disease. My academic interests lie at the intersection of nutrition, public health, and social justice, with a goal of advancing more equitable and effective food policies to improve the health of at-risk populations.

Education

Universidade de Brasília-UnB

Aug 2019 - Dec 2021

MS in Human Nutrition

- Thesis: Obstructive Sleep Apnea Risk in Individuals After Long-term Bariatric Surgery
- Coursework: Biostatistics in Medical Sciences, Epidemiologic Methods, Quantitative Methods in Nutrition 1, Quantitative Methods in Nutrition 2, Bioethics, Justice and Human Rights, Social and Economic Aspects of Eating and Nutrition, Scientific Foundations of Nutrition, Development of Leadership Skills.

Fundação de Apoio à Pesquisa e Estudo na Área da Saúde- FAPES

Mar 2018 - Sep 2019

Graduate Degree (Specialist) in Maternal and Child Nutrition

o Total workload: 420 hours

Secretaria do Estado de Saúde do Distrito Federal - SES/DF

Mar 2011 - Mar 2013

Residency in Clinical Nutrition
• Total workload: 5760 hours

Universidade de Brasília-UnB

Aug 2006 - Jun 2010

BS in Nutrition

• Coursework: Biochemistry and Biophysics, Experimental Biochemistry and Biophysics, Fundamentals of Genetics and Evolution, Basic Histology, Anatomy, Introduction to Public Health, Introduction to Psychology, Elements of Physiology 1, Introduction to Economics, Introduction to Sociology, Introduction to Communication, Fundamental of Food Science, Introduction to Nutrition, General Immunology, Basic Microbiology, Parasitology, Elements of Physiology 2, Human Nutritioni 1, Technology of Agricultural Products, General Pathology, Health and Society1, Nutritional assessment, Human Nutrition 2, Health and Society 2, General Epidemiology, Microbiology and Food Hygiene1, Dietary Technique 1, Food and Nutrition Education, Advanced Seminar in Collective Health Nutrition, Sport Practice 1, Maternal and Infant Nutrition, Gastronomy and Nutrition, Introduction to Business Administration, Nutritiotion in Collective health, Nutritional Pathologyu and Dietotherapy 1, Food Services Management, General Nutrition Outpatient care 1, Advanced topics in health Promotion 1, Internship in Clinical Nutrition, Internishio in Meals Production Management and Internshii in Social Nutrition

Work Experience

Registered dietitian

Brasília, DF

Nutrição Avançada - Outpatient clinic care provider

Mar 2018 - Present

- Provide clinical nutrition services to outpatients, including assessment of individual nutritional status, evaluation, and recommendation of appropriate dietary interventions to improve nutritional status;
- Instructed patients and families regarding their nutritional therapy needs which included dietary interventions, oral diets, tube feedings, and intravenous feedings;

Provided nutrition education and training for patients, parent groups, and professional organizations.

Registered dietitian

Brasília, DF

Children's Hospital of Brasília

Nov 2013 - Sep 2021

- Mentored nutritionist residents in the Nephrology division by leading monthly nutrition journal clubs, as well as supervising dietetic prescriptions and nutritional assessments for pediatric patients;
- Provided clinical nutrition services to inpatients and outpatients, including assessment of individual nutritional status, evaluation, and recommendation of appropriate dietary interventions to improve nutritional status;
- Instructed patients and families regarding their nutritional therapy needs which included dietary interventions, oral diets, tube feedings, and intravenous feedings;
- Provided nutrition education and training for hospital staff, nurses, physicians, graduate and undergraduate students, parent groups, and professional organizations.

Registered Dietitian

Brasília, DF

DaVita Brazil - SEANE

Mar 2013 - Mar 2016

- Assessed, monitored, and analyzed lab test results; educated patients and families on the importance of nutrition awareness in managing chronic kidney disease;
- Participated as a member of DaVita's interdisciplinary care team to provide nutritional services and education according to patients' needs.

Publications

Barbosa ACC, Brison RS, Gomes CC, Wilkinson TJ, Duarte MP, Gruezo ND, Ribeiro HS.Should we consider sarcopenia in pediatric patients with chronic kidney disease? A preliminary cross-sectional analysis. Z Pediatric Nephrology (Berlin, Germany), 11 Aug. 2023.

Barbosa, Ana Carolina S C S et al. Biochemical Markers and Obstructive Sleep Apnea Risk in Individuals After Long-Term Bariatric Surgery Z. Obesity Surgery vol. 32,10 (2022): 3272-3279.

Barbosa, Ana Carolina C et al. Inflammatory response in chronic kidney patients in predialysis and its relation to protein intake C Comunicação em Ciências da Saúde; 23 (2): 111-125, abr.-jun. 2012.

Current Public Policy Project

Researcher & Global Liaison

Rio de Janeiro, RJ

Favela Nutrida Project: Actions for food security of the Black population in the communities Rocinha and Rio das Pedras

Jul 2024 – Present

- o The Favela Nutrida Project is a public policy research initiative led by the *Guetto Institute* ♥, the Oswaldo Cruz Foundation (Fiocruz), and the Pontifical Catholic University of Rio de Janeiro (PUC-Rio) designed to develop public policy strategies for the city and state of Rio de Janeiro, with a focus on ensuring food security in the communities of Rocinha and Rio das Pedras, the largest favelas in Rio de Janeiro;
- Gather, systematize, and compile data related to food security in two favelas/communities, considering its interfaces with the urban and environmental dimensions of the favelas, chronic diseases, and mental health;
- Conduct bibliographic research and collect existing data, such as that from the Instituto Pereira Passos (IPP) database, as well as public data gathered by the UBS (primary health care units in Brazil). This is complemented by field research involving families who use the services provided by Brazil's Unified Health System (SUS).

Conference presentations and lectures

Favela Nutrida Program

Rio de Janeiro, RJ Brazil

Oswaldo Cruz Foundation (Fiocruz) & Pontifical Catholic University of Rio de Janeiro (PUC-Rio)

Oct 2024

o Presentation: "Actions for Food Security of the Black Population in the Communities of Rocinha and Rio

das Pedras", a lecture conducted as part of the "Favela Nutrida" program, a public policy research project led by the Ghetto Institute, the Oswaldo Cruz Foundation and the Pontifical Catholic University of Rio de Janeiro (PUC-Rio).

Diabetes Awareness Program

Cities Changing Diabetes

Philadelphia, PA

Aug 2023

 Presentation: Diabetes and Healthier Food Choices, a lecture conducted as part of the Cities Changing Diabetes Initiative at St. Paul's Baptist Church, a historically African-American congregation at the heart of North Philadelphia.

Global Cuisines Featured: Brazil

Philadelphia, PA

Vetri Community Partnership

Mar 2023

• Cooking Lab: Yuca or Cassava Root, a workshop conducted for the local North Philadelphia community to stimulate global cultural awareness and nutrition education.

Graduate Class, Nephrology Nursing Program

Brasília, DF Brazil

Medical Clinics, Training and Qualification in Health (CTEC)

Mar 2023

• Presentation: Kidney Chronic Disease Nutrition Therapy for Nurses, delivered to graduate students from the Nephrology Nursing Program at CTEC.

Undergraduate Class, Nutrition

Juiz de Fora, MG Brazil

Universidade Federal de Juiz de Fora

Mar 2023

• Presentation: Kidney Chronic Disease Nutrition Therapy for Nurses, delivered to graduate students from the Nephrology Nursing Program at CTEC.

Graduate Program, Physical Education - Group of Study in Physiology and Health (GEFS)

Brasília, DF Brazil

Mar 2023

Faculdade de Educação Física, Universidade de Brasília

• Round Table Discussant: Sarcopenia and Physical Exercise.

The International Congress of Children with Complex Health Conditions

Brasília, DF Brazil

Nov 2018

Children's Hospital of Brasilia (HCB), Brasilia (Brazil)

• Presentation: Nutritional status and laboratory test of patients with glycogen storage disease type monitored at the Children's Hospital of Brasília

Non-profit and outreach education experience

Chief Outreach Program Developer

Philadelphia, PA

Cities Changing Diabetes

Apr 2023 - May 2024

- Provided lectures, and designed nutrition education programs for North Philadelphians, focusing on the management of diabetes for individuals already diagnosed;
- Combined insights and advice to the community with practical ideas about meal planning and nutrition education.

Cooking Lab Nutrition Educator

Philadelphia, PA

Vetri Community Partnership

Oct 2022 - May 2023

- NGO organization that provides nutrition education through cooking labs to more than 20,000 people of all ages across Philadelphia (PA) and Camden (NJ) each year;
- Served at the Vetri Cooking Lab initiative, an after-school program aimed to inspire students to develop the confidence to make nutritious choices for a healthier future;
- Supported educators and designed activities for participants, such as class preparation, and classroom dynamics; instructed students in dealing with food and kitchen items.

Portuguese Teacher to Spanish-Speaking Refugee Children

Philadelphia, PA

Vila International Institute

Jun 2023 - Nov 2023

 NGO founded by Portuguese teachers dedicated to welcoming immigrants in vulnerable conditions through language learning support. o Taught Portuguese to refugee Spanish-speaking children (ages 7-12) currently based in Brazil's capital, Brasília.

International Mission Trip Co-Leader

Ebenezer Baptist Church

Philadelphia, PA Aug 2021 - Present

- o Co-led, along with Ebenezer's Associate Pastor Rev. Bronson Woods, the first mission trip of the Historic Ebenezer Baptist Church, Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. 's congregation, to South America (Rio de Janeiro, Brazil) in the summers of 2022 and also 2024;
- o Set up the delegation's 15 members of Ebenezer meetings and charity activities with local Afro-Brazilian social and civic leaders, such as representatives of the Rio de Janeiro City Hall, the Marielle Franco Institute and Casa Semente, an NGO focused on children's after school programs.

Committee Member, Residency Capstone

Residency in Clinical Nutrition, Hospital Regional Asa Norte

Brasília, DF

Secretaria do Distrito Federal SES/DF

Jan 2021

• Capstone Title: Prevalence of intestinal constipation in chronic hemodialysis patients Author: Natalia Tramontini

Committee Members: Cristiane Ishikawa Ramos, PhD, Ana Carolina Silveira Calado Siqueira Barbosa, MS

Languages

- English Full professional proficiency
- Portuguese Native proficiency
- French Elementary proficiency

$\mathbf{A}\mathbf{ward}$

Recognition of dedication and commitment

Philadelphia, PA

The Historic Ebenezer Baptist Church Recognition Award

Apr 2023 - May 2024

• Award presented by the United States Senator Reverend Dr. Raphael G. Warnock (D-GA), Senior Pastor, in recognition of my dedication and commitment to the Young Adult & Outreach Ministries of the Historic Ebenezer Baptist Church of Atlanta, GA., Dr. Martin Luther King Jr.'s congregation.